<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="YES">
  <!-- MONSTERS -->
  <monster>
    <name>Hug Hug</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <ac>13</ac>
    <hp>3</hp>
    <str>8</str>
    <con>10</con>
    <dex>13</dex>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>9</wis>
    <cha>8</cha>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <speed>6 sqr/30 ft.</speed>
    <languages>Common, Goblin</languages>
    <cr>1/8</cr>
    <trait>
      <name>Bushwhacker</name>
      <text>During the first round of combat, Hug Hug has advantage on attack rolls against any target that has a lower initiative.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Stealthy</name>
      <text>Hug Hug gains a +5 bonus to all checks to avoid detection.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Melee Attack—Club</name>
      <text>+4 to hit (reach 1; one creature). Hit: 4 (1d4 + 2) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>|4|1d4+2</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Ranged Attack—Sling</name>
      <text> +4 to hit (range 6/12; one creature). Hit: 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>|4|1d4+2</attack>
    </action>
    <description>
The lone surviving goblin cowers under the mine cart until a character lifts it, at which point he scampers out and attempts to run away. The goblin, Hug Hug, isn’t looking for a fight. If the characters are friendly toward him, he gladly fights by their side (avoiding melee when- ever possible). For a goblin, he’s uncharacteristically generous and loyal. He speaks broken Common and Dwarvish, and he knows enough of the latter to translate the runes found throughout the mine.
Hug Hug has enough food to survive another day or two on his own, but he’s not shy about begging from well-equipped adventurers. He gets his name from a natural tendency to hug others when scared.
Roleplaying Notes: Hug Hug should be played as a likable character. He views his liberators as his best chance for survival but knows nothing about the Mines of Madness and makes a poor guide; he and his kin stumbled on the entrance and decided to investigate on a whim. The survivors of the tunnel collapse (see area 2) didn’t get far before they were set upon by the cocka- trices; consequently, Hug Hug hasn’t explored much of the mine.
If the characters spare Hug Hug’s life, he gives them his only treasure: 1 copper piece. Even if the adventurers might find him a useful companion, they could choose to sacrifice him in area 27 instead of another party member. If you roleplay Hug Hug well, it should be a heartbreaking decision for good-aligned characters to make.
    </description>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Giant Lizark Skeleton</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <ac>11</ac>
    <hp>9</hp>
    <speed>6, climb 4</speed>
    <senses>darkvision 12</senses>
    <str>13</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>10</con>
    <int>2</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>3</cha>
    <cr>1/8</cr>
    <languages>-</languages>
    <trait>
      <name>Immunities:</name>
      <text>The skeleton cannot be charmed, frightened, or put to sleep. It is immune to disease and poison.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Resistance:</name>
      <text>The skeleton is resistant to piercing damage.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Vulnerability:</name>
      <text>The skeleton is vulnerable to bludgeoning damage.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Melee Attack-Bite:</name>
      <text>+5 to hit (reach 1; one creature). Hit: 7 (1d8 + 3) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>|5|1d8+3</attack>
    </action>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Dwarf Skeleton</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <ac>13</ac>
    <hp>9</hp>
    <speed>5</speed>
    <senses>darkvision 12</senses>
    <str>11</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>10</con>
    <int>6</int>
    <wis>8</wis>
    <cha>3</cha>
    <languages>Common</languages>
    <action>
      <name>Melee Attack-War Pick:</name>
      <text>+5 to hit (reach 1; one creature). Hit: 4 (1d8) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>|4|1d8</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Ranged Attack-Throwing Axe:</name>
      <text>+5 to hit (range 4/12; one creature).Hit: 3 (1d6) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>|3|1d6</attack>
    </action>
    <trait>
      <name>Immunities:</name>
      <text>The skeleton cannot be charmed, frightened, or put to sleep. It is immune to disease and poison.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Resistance:</name>
      <text>The skeleton is resistant to piercing damage.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Vulnerability:</name>
      <text>The skeleton is vulnerable to bludgeoning damage.</text>
    </trait>
  </monster>

  <monster>
    <name>Oink Zombie</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <ac>8</ac>
    <hp>9</hp>
    <speed>4</speed>
    <senses>Dark vision 12</senses>
    <str>15</str><dex>6</dex><con>10</con>
    <int>6</int><wis>7</wis><cha>9</cha>
    <languages>understands Common</languages>
    <cr>1/4</cr>
    <trait>
      <name>Destroyed by Sunlight:</name>
      <text> The zombie is destroyed instantly by sunlight.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Immunities:</name>
      <text>The zombie cannot be charmed, frightened, or put to sleep. It is immune to disease and poison.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Zombie Fortitude:</name>
      <text>
        When the zombie takes damage that would reduce it to 0 hit points, it must make a DC 10 Constitution saving throw. It fails the saving throw automatically if the damage is the result of a critical hit. Successful Save: The zombie is instead reduced to 1 hit point.
      </text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Melee Attack-Long Sword:</name>
      <text>+5 to hit (reach 5 ft.; one creature). Hit: 6 (1d8 + 2) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>|5|1d8+2</attack>
    </action>
  </monster>

  <monster>
    <name>Death Stalker</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <ac>10</ac>
    <hp>4</hp>
    <speed>6</speed>
    <senses>darkvision 12</senses>
    <str>9</str><dex>11</dex><con>10</con>
    <int>4</int><wis>10</wis><cha>10</cha>
    <languages>understands Common</languages>
    <cr>1/8</cr>
    <trait>
      <name>Immunities:</name>
      <text> The deathstalker is immune to necrotic damage.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Fear of Felines:</name>
      <text>On its turn, the deathstalker must move its speed away from any cat that it can see. If it is within 10 feet of a cat and cannot move away, it explodes as a reaction (see Actions below).</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Explode:</name>
      <text> The deathstalker explodes in a 10-foot-radius sphere, destroying itself. All other creatures in the area of effect must make a DC 11 Dexterity saving throw. Failed Save: 7 (2d6) necrotic damage. Successful Save: Half damage.</text>
      <attack>||2d6</attack>
    </action>
  </monster>

  <!-- Items -->
  <!-- Spells -->

</compendium>